<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: sapui5 | Second Phase Solutions]]></title>
  <link href="http://jasper07.github.io/blog/categories/sapui5/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jasper07.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-01-05T10:38:26+11:00</updated>
  <id>http://jasper07.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[John Patterson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Beyond SAP Fiori's 1:1:3]]></title>
    <link href="http://jasper07.github.io/blog/2015/01/04/beyond-sap-fioris-1-1-3/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-04T22:48:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://jasper07.github.io/blog/2015/01/04/beyond-sap-fioris-1-1-3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><script async="true" class="speakerdeck-embed" data-id="8086964076310132049b22819074b7b4" src="//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js"> </script></p>

<p>A few people have me to share the slides from the talk i gave at SAP Dcode 2014 Las Vegas</p>

<p>The talk was around using best practices to overcome some of the challenges you will face developing and maintaining SAPUI5 applications for the Enterprise.</p>

<p>The takeaway points</p>

<p><strong>1. Follow JS Best Practices</strong> - a lot of the tutorials and documentation for SAPUI5 is centered around using Eclipse as an IDE, in my opinoin which is shared by many others there is no one size fits all and it is better to build your developer toolset from the ground up, using applications that you are familiar with and add additional functionality as it is needed rather than start with something that is preconfigured, bloated and hard to change. This sections covered thngs like automating develop, build and deploy tasks using Grunt or Gulp, using a distributed version control system like git to reduce the risk of introducing errors and ensuring quality, following best practices to improve the performance of your apps etc.</p>

<p><strong>2. Dont Build Big Apps</strong> - this is true for any programming paradigm, dont build big apps, build lots of small ones. In this section i covered the different techniques available for modularizing your code in small units, and then how to bring the small units together using routing to determine the state of the application, ie what views need to be visible and what data needs to be shown and then how to use events to seamlessely navigate through the different states of the application, allowing the</p>

<p><strong>3. Use fit-for-purposes API&rsquo;s</strong> - the inside-out approach for creating services with Netweaver Gateway sounds like a good idea, take an existing BAPI and expose it. This approach lends itself to complexity, for starters BAPI&rsquo;s have to cater for lots of different scenarios, so its likely that there is too much functionality for you want, and as you come accross business logic and functionality not available in the BAPI developers will often try and build this into the front end. In this section i talked about taking a model first approach, let the data drive the application not the other way around, flesh out the screens you have designed and build an infomation architecture from the data requirement, use this as a basis for a data model to build your services from, at this point you can create Mock Data which will allow the SAPUI5 developer to quickly build screens and validate the data model, there are a couple of other benefits of using Mock Data first, it means the development can happen in parallel and independent of the backend ABAP developers, using the MockData server makes it easy to create Unit and End-to-End tests allowing you to quickly find issues, perfect for quickly validating new feature request and bug fixes</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
