<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: mobile | ]]></title>
  <link href="http://jasper07.secondphase.com.au/blog/categories/mobile/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jasper07.secondphase.com.au/"/>
  <updated>2015-02-20T04:08:46+11:00</updated>
  <id>http://jasper07.secondphase.com.au/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[John Patterson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mobile first in China]]></title>
    <link href="http://jasper07.secondphase.com.au/blog/2015/02/19/mobile-first-in-china/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-19T18:03:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://jasper07.secondphase.com.au/blog/2015/02/19/mobile-first-in-china</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I am currently in China on a working holiday. Today is Chinese New Year, a time to be retrospective and a second chance for me to start acting on some resolutions that slipped.</p>

<p>My observation is China is a contrast in technology trends, mobile adoption is moving faster than anywhere else I have been and in the wake a legacy of Windows XP on the desktop is refusing to go away.</p>

<p>Everywhere you look you see Iphone 6s and Galaxy Note 3s, prior to coming to China I knew that &ldquo;brand new&rdquo; mobile phones were fashionable, and I discounted as a younger generation fascinated with status and Western Culture. Being here has given me a different perspective. Not having access to Google, YouTube or Facebook has not slowed down technology adoption, from what I can see China is ahead of the curve when it comes to mobility, both in terms of adoption and how the mobile device is being used.</p>

<p>The stats are amazing <a href="http://www.hihuadu.com/2015/02/03/chinese-mobile-phone-users-to-557-million-or-858-of-total-internet-users-11116.html">Chinese mobile phone users to 557 million or 85.8 % of total Internet users</a>, there is 94.5% mobile penetration and from what I can see, like their cars, they are all brand new and better than mine!</p>

<p>The recent article form Smashing Magazine <a href="http://www.smashingmagazine.com/2015/02/13/china-web-design-trends-2015/">China’s Bleeding Edge: Web Design Trends 2015</a> is a really good read and highlights some of what I am seeing here <b>WeChat, light apps and QR codes</b> everywhere. The high level summary, one mobile platform in WeChat, it covers all social media, news, blogging, e-commerce, banking, IM, Group Chat needs and more. WeChat has over 400 million users, of that China makes up atleast 80%, however you look at it that is still a lot of use outside of China. Because it is the number one app with a built in web browser here, it has meant that the way websites are built has changed, they need to cater for the mobile first in the form of HTML5 single page &ldquo;light apps&rdquo;. Having a big number of users means that it could expand and innovate quickly, everywhere you look here you see QR Codes, in shop windows, on products, on billboards etc.</p>

<p>On the flip side of this mobile first adoption is that it is leaving behind an aging desktop legacy. I am lead to believe based on observations and recent articles that the number one desktop OS here in China is still Windows XP. This is no surprise to me, the majority of big clients and Government agencies I work for are also still predominantly on Windows XP. Change moves slower in big enterprise and government. However in Australia a lot of the customers I work for have adopted Google Chrome for XP as a way of &ldquo;keeping the lights on just that little longer&rdquo;, it&rsquo;s seen as way of rolling out a nice UX like SAP Fiori to users on kit that was written off years ago, putting Chrome on XP is the proverbial lipstick on a pig. This trend will change as Microsoft dropping support of XP soon, I believe it is April 2015, around about that time Google has said they will no longer support Chrome for XP also. Hopefully this will lead businesses to ask themselves &ldquo;can we afford to keep supporting XP?&rdquo;&#8221;</p>

<p>The stats say there is a large Chrome user base, however from what I can see here in China based on my own access, using Chrome on XP is probably not an option and I am not reading or seeing any uptake for browsers like Firefox and Opera either. <a href="https://www.modern.ie/en-us/ie6countdown">Modern.ie</a> shows whilst dropping rapidly, 3% of China still uses IE6 for a browser and of the remaining 10% that makes up the Desktop portion, aging IE browser make up a large portion. This definitely presents a challenge for Enterprise Software or start-up companies thinking of breaking into China. Support IE8, or hope that users will only want to use the web kit/chrome browser on their phone, or break out the QR codes and install the WeChat SDK. I think Smashing Magazine article says it all &ldquo;Do China right or don’t bother&rdquo;.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
